Hello everyone, and welcome. Thank you
for joining us today for this
conversation on a topic that is
becoming increasingly important for
everyone working with content. As AI
reshapes how people discover and use
information, we are under growing
pressure to deliver content that is
precise, structured, and context aware. We
are no longer creating content just for
human readers. We are creating it for
the systems that help humans find what
they need. And that shift puts a
spotlight on the foundations of
information architecture, the models, the
metadata, the relationships that make
content understandable to both. People
and machines and to help us
unpack what this means in practice
and how teams can build content
ecosystems that are ready for intelligent
delivery. We are joined today by
Rahel, who has been shaping this
conversation for years. So I'm delighted
to introduce Rahel Anne Bailie. And
those very few people who
don't know her.
Then there's a quick introduction.
Rahel is uh, globally respected
expert in content strategy and
content operations. She's known for
her ability to diagnose complex
ecosystems and build scalable standard
driven operations. She's also the
co-author of two influential. Looks
content strategy connecting the dots
between business brands and benefits and
also the language of content strategy her
work has helped organizations around the
world treat content as our true business
that. So Ryan, thank you so much for
joining us thrilled to have you here and
happy to be here thank you for.
Fighting me. Great. Uh,
so, uh, dear audience, before we dive
in, just a few quick housekeeping notes.
I've also pinned them in the chat
for you. I'm recording this conversation.
This will be shared on LinkedIn after
the event and since we have a
lot to cover, so we will open
up for Q&A. And your feedback at the
end of this conversation. In the
meantime, if any question comes to your
mind at any point, please drop it in the
chat and I'll gather them and invite you
to unmute during the Q&A if you would
like to ask your questions directly to
Ryan and in the due course if you run
into any. Critical issues. Feel free to
log out and rejoin using the meeting
link, which is also there in the chat.
OK, with that, let's begin.
Let's begin with a look at the
challenges that our information
architects and technical writers face
today. So as we move towards AI
driven content delivery, long standing
information architecture challenges come
into sharper focus. Challenges that can
lead even the most sophisticated AI tools
to return results that feel. Irrelevant
and misleading, for example, fragmented
content or inconsistent metadata being
the most visible challenge. So right
from your perspective, what are the
challenges like? Which are the hidden
challenges that information architects
need to address for AI powered
content delivery?
Well, I would like to to
kind of frame this by saying
that it doesn't really matter where
you are working, whether you're in
a very small organization or very
large organization, a lot of the
challenges are the same because what
happens is that. We were told
to use AI and, you know, do
do AI, and nobody really starts thinking
about the strategic part of what are
we trying to accomplish because there's
no single right way to do, you
know, to use AI. How you use
it is going to depend on what.
Want to do with it. So we have,
uh, we all have legacy content and we
started in this business. I've been in
this business for a long, long time. So
the tools that we had at the beginning
didn't really they, they weren't fit for
purpose for the way we have to deliver
content today. So everything has kind of
grown organically. You know, we started
off using word perfect and then it
was, um, word and then it was,
um Framemaker and then it was and,
you know, it just kind of grew
and grew and grew. And so if
we were to take those documents that
we were doing. Back then,
because a lot of us are working
on machines or software services or
whatever it may be that have existed
for many, many, many years. So we
still go back to some of those
legacy documents and we we don't have
the kind of robustness. That is
needed, uh, in today's world. So you
mentioned, for example, missing metadata.
Well, that's an obvious one because, you
know, we're using Word perfect or
Microsoft Word. You can't componentize
content and you can't put the, the
kind of metadata on it that you
want and you combine that. With not
knowing um, who your market is and
what the strategy is supposed to be,
then how are you supposed to know
how you need to tag it up?
So one of the common things I
see is when, um, like the United
States is such a big market, they.
Often start with just domestic product
and so you don't have to tag it up with
the country or the language or any of
those things because it's one market. And
so if you know that you're going to be
expanding into many markets, then you
might start tagging it up differently for
those markets. And if you're in things
like, you know automotive, there's a.
Ohh, well known, uh, well well known
to people who've been in the industry
as long as me. Um, example of
someone who wanted a.
Side mirror or a wing mirror, they would
call it in the UK for the passenger side
of a car and it came and it was the wrong
side of the car. Because in the UK they
drive on the other side of the road. So
the passengers are on the left and they
wanted the the, the, the wing mirror for
the right. So when you have those kinds
of things. If you know that you're,
you're, you are going to be expanding
into those countries, you start thinking
about those things like, ohh, I need to
be able to tag this up in a
different way. And so we haven't done
that. No matter whether you're, you know,
in like as in a small company or
a big company. So it's kind of
a ubiquitous problem because how we
deliver content today is so much more
complex than how we delivered it even 10
years ago or five years ago. And now
with AI coming in, it's so important to
have all the pieces in place to be
able to deliver the content. The way you
need to. Well, that's very
interesting. So I think there is an
angle of localization also that you bring
up as one of the challenges. Yeah,
yes. And localization can mean multiple
languages or it could mean the same
language, but just in different markets.
Yeah, certainly. So that's a helpful look
at the. And then just beneath the
surface, right, building on that, I would
love to shift focus towards the practical
side of preparing for AI powered content
delivery while addressing these
challenges. So tell me, when information
architects and technical writers are
planning for this future, what key
considerations they should keep in mind?
Well, there are a number of things
and I think it's important to look
at content holistically and to look at
the system holistically. So one of the
things that you might want to think
of is how, what are you using?
Is it a large language model? Is
it a smaller language model?Is
it something in house? Are you doing
something using third party agents? You
know, are you using Agenta Ki and
and what are where are all these
things coming from? Because we know. So
we all know about hallucinations now. We
don't even have to say that at
anymore. Because we're so familiar with
the idea that these large language
models can go off the rails, but how
do we keep them on the rails? So
do we use a RAG model, for example?
Then what kind of RAG model and is?
How are we doing the prompts and and
how are we?What
are we sharing inadvertently with
the world as opposed to
what are we what do
we need to, you know,
the intellectual property that we
should keep within our organization
and then, you know, when
we're creating the. If you're
familiar with Lance Cummings, Doctor
Lance Cummings, he talks about how
to structure prompts for technical
writing and he will talk about
the how you give the AI
a persona like such as you
know you are an expert in
electrical engineering. In this field,
for example, but you also have to give
a persona for the audience. And so now
it's not enough to just give the one
persona for this end, you need to to
give it for the other end. And then
you're creating very specific
instructions, but you're also
constraining the model. To say like for
example, we are only looking at this
body of documents, if you think about
this and they call it like the
open world versus the closed world model.
So the open world model, you say
we want to get insights. However, in
our business it's not so much about.
Getting insights for example, like how
many customers took things out of their
shopping cart before they checked out,
right? I mean, that would be the the kind
of this example of what kind of insights
do we see about the market in general.
That's for a different department. We
have the the problem of we have a big
body of content. And users want
to find that that one thing
amongst it's like that needle in
the haystack. And we want to
deliver it on that first try
because people are starting to become
accustomed to being able to to
get that answer. On the first try,
and this is how some organizations
actually set up their metrics, how what
is the successful answer is when they can
get it on the first try and not have
to fiddle around with the keywords or
they don't have to call customer service,
they could just ask and get the answer.
And so how do we make that happen?
On the one hand, we've got this body
of content, so it's closed and we want
to get an answer out of that. We
don't have this big world problem, but
what we do have is a content curation
situation. I don't want to call it a
problem because I think it's actually an
opportunity for us as writers. To to
influence how well the content is
delivered. So it's not just enough
to curate the content, which needs
to be done, but we also
have to curate the context. And
so when you combine those two
things, we become more of. Curators,
then actual writers, because you can get
a lot of information that's already been
written in your that you wrote last
year or two years ago or five
years ago. And now the challenge is
how do I get that pulled out
and given to or delivered to the
audience?Without delivering them like,
you know, the whole essay, the whole PDF
or the whole chapter or the whole
section, whatever it may be, they just
want that one piece of information like
at what temperature does this product
melt? Well, you would want them to say
this product melts at this temperature
and and that's it, right?So how
do you get that pulled out? So
we're we are now becoming curators as
opposed to, I don't mean just
disparagingly, but only if, if we combine
our skill set to only writing, then
we're missing a trick here because now
we need to be curators. It's almost
like the managing editor. Of a, of
a magazine, right? You want to be able
to see what goes in, what complements
each other, how people are going to find
that information. And one of the other
things is around content maintenance,
because I call it The Dirty little secret
of our industry is that it's not so
much the cost of the creation. Creation,
content creation costs money. You know,
not, um, I'm not downplaying that,
but let's say it costs.
£100 to create an article
because it takes you that
long to do the the
drafting, the writing, the getting
the sign off and so
on. Now that gets propagated
maybe into 12 places and
now you have 13. Copies to
update so when you go to to update it,
not only do you still have to do all the
same steps, you have to draft you have to
yeah, you have well, first of all you
have to find your original and then you
have to draft the update. Then you have
to go get it signed off and so on and
so forth so you're not really. Saving
much time there, but now you
have to go find the other
12 instances and update them as
well. And so this maintenance challenge
is, is compounded with AI if
you're not really looking at that
kind of single sourcing and robust
reuse. Strategy so you have to think
about the maintenance challenges and
everybody's maintenance challenges will
be slightly different, but the big thing
now is everyone wants to deliver through
some sort of a natural language query, in
other words, a chat bot. So you know,
here's the body of content and now
there's going to be this chat. Thought
that asks a question you can ask in
natural language and the L will interpret
it and it will generate an answer based
on the information. And so that brings
its own challenges because it's no longer
like, ohh, let's create a PDF or let's
create some HTML pages. Now it's hey,
where are those micro facts and how are
we going to take?Those and make
them deliverable by an LM in a
way that will be useful for the
user. So if you have 12 products,
uh, let's take a printer. How to
change the printer cartridge? This has
always been one of my bug bears.
I'm spatially challenged. So I'm always
looking at the cartridge and going, I
don't know how this goes in and I want
to look it up now. If I say, how
do I change a printer cartridge, I'm
going to get very generic things like
open the cover, uh, take out the old
cartridge, put in the new cartridge. But
it's like that's not. Answering the
question, the question is which direction
is up and which is, you know, what should
be facing me and how do I click it
in and so on. So how does it know?
So it has to be tagged with the model
number because if it's not the model
number, it won't know which of the 200
printers that you make is the right one.
And so they all have different shapes and
sizes of cartridges. And so those are the
kinds of things that we think about now
is how do I make sure that the delivery
system, whether that's a content delivery
platform or a web series of web pages or
a customer support portal or whatever it
may be, how do I make sure that?
They can get the right answer. And in
some industries, like for a printer
cartridge, if I have to ask two or
three times, I will eventually find the
answer and it won't be critical. But if
this is a medical device or if this
is something, you know, financial where
you could stand to lose a lot of
money. If you don't choose the right
option for your investment, you know,
that can be quite life changing for
people. And so you know, the the
challenge is to get it right and
to get it right the first time.
And and that's not something that.
We're used to having to do
before, and so that's creating like
this whole other level of awareness
that hasn't been there. Umm, So
now all the challenges could compounded
basically. Now the technical writers or
information architects have to consider
about all possible personas. That might
be interacting with a particular system
or content system to get the answers.
And on top of that, they have
to write everything possible that these
people might ask, you know, as many
things that they can understand and
organize it so that AI can deliver
content based on that. So that's, yes,
it's it, it, it means that we have
to think more carefully about what we're
writing. So I sometimes use that example
of, um, when we used to document like
all the fields, right? So there's a date
field. So you say you enter the date
and the date field that tells nobody
anything. What it, what would be
useful is to say what, uh, what's
uh, the, the format, what date format
do you have to use? Is it
day, day, month, month, year, or you
know, year, year, year, year, or is
it, uh, year, year, year, year?
Month to month, date, date. And if
you're in the system itself, you might
be able to see that you know
is grayed out in the the form
field. But if you are looking for
something that's more sophisticated than
the date and you need to find
that information, how do you?
How is it written so that it's useful
to your user? And that becomes a bigger
challenge because you can't just kind of
sleepwalk through your job. You have to
really be out there thinking how what
does the user need? And you know that
thing about how we never seem to.
Yeah, um, time with users, right. So you
say, well, well, how many Internet users
have you interviewed? Ohh, no, no, we
don't get to talk to the users. Well,
now it's important to understand what
they need and how they need it so
that you can deliver that information. So
I saw a. Uh,
a presentation where they were
talking about, um, lifts, elevators
and so to, um, to
do elevator repair, they would
have the directions, but they
found that it was easier
to teach how to do
the elevator repairs. By building
a plywood elevator safely on
the ground and having AR
glasses or VR glasses, AR
glasses and having them go
into this environment and.
Do it as if they're working on it and
then the instructions would show in the
glasses. Well, how are you taking that
into account if you don't know that
that's how they're using it?
Right. So those are those are things that
we have to think about now that we didn't
really have to think about before. So
it's really making us wonder kind of what
are we doing and why are we doing it and
how are we doing it so that it's useful
because at some point what we're doing
may not be useful anymore.
So now it becomes important we understand
our users, the content users, what they
need and how the content is being
delivered. So all these things we have
to factor in when we write, hey,
you know, even put pen to paper
or whatever type anything. So we have
to consider. All these things beforehand
and plan them. So, yeah, so that's
a great tool for laying out all
those constraints.
So it's began preparing for AI powered
delivery. It is about building the right
foundation so that content can actually
move through the intelligence systems
that now organizations are putting
together so that the content is accurate
and consistent. Now
when teams start putting together
these systems, what do you
see as essential building blocks
or an information architecture that
truly supports AI driven content
delivery?So
we are talking about building
blocks. Yes. One of the
things that that's been happening
recently is that we started
an association called Kinetic Kinetic
Council and I coined the
the term kinetic information because.
Penises, the definition of kinesis
is that that there's an
outside force you have. You
have something that's innate and
or static, and then an
outside force comes and it
there's movement in response to
this external stimulus. And when
you think about a, um, content in
an AI context, that's exactly what
happens. We create all the content and
we keep it in a repository somewhere,
whether that's in a CMS or a
CDP or within our CCMS, wherever we,
we hold it and then an AI
and an LM or. The CMS
or something comes and calls that content
and then that content gets delivered for
a user to one or more users. And
so when we think about content, now we
have to think about the, you know,
kinetic, kinetic content. So we have to
think about content as having Kinesis and
to do that. We can't think of
just an authoring system. So some people
will say, well, you know, I put
my content into a CCMS and now
it's componentized and I've got metadata
on it. I'm done. And you can't
really think about it that way. You
have to think about an authoring system.
So ideally a CMS or something
similar, something that lets you put
lots of semantic metadata on it
and then you think about the
semantics. So semantics are, you know,
a knowledge graph of some sort.
The red graph seems to be.
The thing to use at least right now, so
you have a a knowledge graph that will
create all the relationships for you. And
then and when you think about
relationships, you think, think of like
how a mind map works, right? You have all
these concepts that connect to each other
and then they connect to other things and
so on. So. The, the, UM,
the knowledge graph is kind of that
same. It operates that same way. It's
not just a taxonomy, It's not just,
um, hierarchical is forming
relationships. And to do that is great,
but then you have to constrain it
as well. So that's where the rag.
Comes in. So all of all of this
is part of the orchestration layer. So
the orchestration of the content is like
once it's written and once you've added
metadata, then it goes into kind of into
the oven and gets baked with, you know,
with the help of the knowledge graph and
and. And you know the rag model
that helps with the delivery and then you
get to the delivery end. The delivery end
could be so many different things. Now
it's it's yes, you could still have a
PDF, you could have HTML, you could have.
AR, VR content delivery platforms marked
down like there's so many ways that
it could be delivered. So you have
to think of this in the holistic
sense of a content ecosystem and not
just like a tool, because whatever
whichever tool you pick, it's only. Part
of the puzzle and so you have to think
about it in the the bigger sense and in
particularly when you get into multiple.
The languages and multiple markets,
because that becomes quite complex.
Umm, you have to factor in machine
translation, etcetera. So, but there's
one thing I've, uh, that comes to
my mind. We had, we have had
so many complex CMS CMS systems so
far and what I see the content
delivery when it happens via a digital
assistant or say. GPT or
uh, cloud, uh, third party
agents or an organization's own
digital assistant, they read the
information from flat files and
in knowledge graphs, right? Which
are basically specially designed a
particular format of information. In
the relationships and information are
defined. Work in that
scenario is the use of the complex
content hierarchies that we had in our
legacy content and the CMS that we
had, you know, the various containers and
folders and directory systems and
whatnot. So what happens to that? So.
So, um.
I'll answer this question in
kind of 2 levels. So
the first thing is we
can still can I, can
I use unstructured content? Yes,
it can. Will it give
you highly accurate answers? No,
the more structure. To add
to the content, the better.
AI can use it and part
of it is because it understands
the context. So if you are
going to ask, I've got a
few examples but one that just
comes to mind is at one
point I was. Asking and and
this is this isn't even AI, this
is just with Google search. I was
asking about wine bars and so they
showed me all of the the establishments
in my neighborhood that I could go
to meet friends to drink wine, but
I wanted to buy a piece of
furniture. So when you're looking
at wine bars, you have the schema for
venue because venue is, uh, you know, in
schema.org venue is, you know, wine bar
could be a venue, but as soon as
I say I want to buy a wine
bar, then they know, they understand the
context is that by. Equals product equals
show furniture and you'll get a
completely different set of search
results. Now when you take that
and you amplify it so they
say garbage in garbage out and
so it's like garbage in is
amplified garbage out for AI and
what we. You don't want is
is that amplification of poor content. So
if you have a little bit of
structure, like in Microsoft Word using
the style sheets, you've got a little
bit of a structure, but it doesn't
tell you enough to be useful. So
an example would be. Uh, and this
came from a vendor who was showing us
their software. If you have, um, a
document like a Word document that was
saved as a PDF and you have in there
heading 1 heading to, but by the time you
get to heading through, you're just using
italics. So you get like, what is the
dosage of this medication?So here's about
the medication. Here's the dosage. And
then it goes like for adults,
for teenagers, for children, for infants.
So you've got four different doses
for four different audiences. And if
you're just using a, you know,
a PDF. The the the LM
might pick up the wrong one.
Because it won't know
from the structure.
There's not enough structure to inform it
accurately, so it might pick up the right
one and it might not pick up the
right one depending on how it was written
editorially. Now if you have more
structure, then it's going to be able to
pick up the right one because the the
metadata. On it and the knowledge graph
will have said that this is about this
product and it's about this dosage and
it's for this audience and it might even
go as far as it's in this market because
in this country we don't sell that
product. In this country we sell that
product and in this this other country we
sell the product but under a different
name. And so it can tell all
those relationships and it can deliver
the right thing to the right person. So
the the more structure you have, the more
context the AI understands and the more
accurately it can deliver.
The results and there is
you know the IRS, which
is a delivery schema especially
meant for technical documentation.
They've run different tests on
it and it's it once
if you have highly structured
content plus. A knowledge graph
plus the using IDs, you
get very very high quality
results consistently. You know, even
when you run the test
2030405060 times you're getting
consistently high quality results, but
without that if you are
only using the LM.
And you didn't have the knowledge graph
and the the semantic layer and and so
on. And you're just running it on Word
docs or PDFs. It's somewhere around 25%
compared to 85%. So that's a huge
difference, right?The
structure means, uh, difference here. So
what our legacy content, if it was
well structured, will serve us well. Uh,
so we, yes, definitely. And when I
say structure, I'm not meaning editorial
conventions like, you know.
But the most important paragraph at
the right after the H1? That's
an editorial convention. I'm talking
about the semantics where you actually
add the metadata on to make
it very explicit to the machines
to understand what that particular
sentence or paragraph. This section is
about. Umm, so that's
great insight. Thanks for breaking that
down, Ryan. And once these foundational
building blocks of, you know, semantics,
orchestration, delivery, they are all in
place. The next challenge is figuring
out how teams can actually work
with them. Day-to-day. So, looking
at the practical side of
implementation, what day-to-day practices
should information architects and
technical writers should follow so
as they prepare for a
given content delivery?
I think that it, it, there is no
kind of 1 formula. Everything is going to
be different depending on what you're
trying to achieve. So the first thing you
have to do is focus on what you're
trying to achieve, what is the business
goal? And then you determine which
practices are right for your organization
and then. What is right for your
team? So you need to kind of
work backwards from that and you you
need to use a fit for purpose
tools. So if if your company is
expecting you to do miracles with
Microsoft Word, it's not going to happen.
It just won't happen. And so you.
Want to have some sort of a tool, a
production grade authoring tool. This is
what I'm um.
You know, we use the term CMS, but
outside of our industry, nobody ever
understands what that is. But really you
want an authoring tool that is, um, you
know, they want you to, to run a
content production line. Well, then you
need a production line tool, right? So I.
And sometimes use the donut factory as an
example. It's like you can make Donuts in
your home kitchen using the little
silicon mold where you can do 6 at
a time, but that's not going to help
you supply an entire bakery. If you're
doing the bakery, you need, you know, the
big dough mixer and the big extruder
that. Spits out 24 doughnuts at a
time and puts them on an assembly line
to go into the fryer. And so to,
to get that, um, that kind of operational
efficiency, you need to be able to, um.
Tag up your contents and so on. It's not
enough to take the content and then throw
it over the wall with the big long e-mail
and expect somebody else to read your
mind about which content goes with which
audience and so on. You need to be able
to do it because you know why you're
writing it, right? So as you're writing a
particular sentence, it's like, ohh, I
better tag that. Happens with, you know,
um. Monaco only or whatever
he'll, uh, Luxembourg only. So when
you're creating this, you have to kind of
work backwards. And we're used to doing
that in, in content where they need this
delivered at this time. And how many
weeks do we need to be able to
do, you know, to, to have to do
these things?And we work backwards all
the time for scheduling. So we also need
to work backwards when it comes to, you
know, what our practices are to be able
to say OK and to be able to do to
get this result, we need to be able to do
this. And to do that, we need to be able
to do that. To do that, I need these
tools. To be able to accomplish all of
this. Hmm ohh but didn't grant
too much.
Alright, I do understand that
because we are looking at,
uh, wide spectrum of, uh,
you know, uh, availability of
tools. They are large organizations
that provide their employees with
in-house AI, digital agents, alms
and. Cortana playgrounds, dedicated
playgrounds to test their prompts,
etcetera. And on the other hand, there
are startups that don't have that kind
of, you know, uh, situation. They have
resource scarcity. So
we are looking at both ends
of spectrum here where people have
a lot, but still they, uh,
struggle with fragmented content and
spread across, you know, content league
of sorts where a lot of
different pieces of contents are there,
video, audio, text, whatnot. And on the
other hand, there could be a startup that
is just, you know, putting together their
operations for this first time, telling
their technical writers, all you have is
GitHub knock you hours get it Then we
will give you add the most one ChatGPT or
rather sorry, open AI license. That's it.
That's what you are getting. So it can
be. A little bit of a difficult
situation for technical writers in either
situation to understand what their makes
use of in their current setup, so
I think. We have to
spell it out. If you can give both
situations some kind of, you know, best
practice 1 where there is a lot but very
little guidance and the other place where
they are starting from the scratch and
they have the ability to build something
from the ground but they don't have many
resources. If you could give some kind
of. Price for that? Well,
um. So
first of all, the field is moving
very fast. So every few months there's
something new, something new and
something new. So even what I tell
you today might be outdated next week.
But, um, if you're just starting.
Or you are a very small team or
a team of 1. Then you could you
could do something like um.
You could use
markdown and.
It's not going to be perfect, but
it's better than nothing. So you could
use Markdown and GitHub. You could also
get an A license to Oxygen and
use GitHub. And they've made this kind
of like a a very modest CMS
for single person. So, you
know, you could you, you could
do it that way and then,
um, you may not have a
knowledge graph, but you can certainly.
Um.
Use whatever information architecture and
taxonomy tools that you have, even
if it's an Excel spreadsheet. You
can make your taxonomy in the
Excel spreadsheet and use those. I
guess it's like consistent tagging,
right? So that's what's important.
And it, you know, you, you
start with that when you're a
bigger team then you will, you
might even have in-house created systems,
right? Because there will be other
departments working on other projects and
there might be things that you
can. Um, kind of tag
onto their license or, uh, reuse
some of the, the work that
they've done and it won't all
fit, but sometimes you can, you
know, get kick started that way
there you probably will have things
like a. The CMS and,
uh, the AI and the CMS is
going to be for kind of editorial
quality. It won't give you much more
than that. You'll have some sort of
a knowledge graph or some sort of
semantic tool and then you may use
a content delivery platform. You
know, such as like a fluid
topics or, um, uh, there are
a few others that are kind
of attached to a CMS and,
um, that will, that will alleviate
your burden a little bit because
the things that you used to
have to do. Manually in
in knowledge graph software or
in taxonomy software. Now the
LM and in the the
delivery platform will take some
of that burden on. So
it's it works very differently
so I think for me.
It's it's the idea that you have to
kind of keep up with what's going on
in the marketplace.
You know, just stay informed because
there might not be something for you
today, but there could be something for
you 3 months from now, but you
won't find out about it unless you
are keeping your ear to the ground.
Yeah, so they can listen to your
podcast as well as. Meet your
LinkedIn post about this to learn more
about that uh. Now
data does lend itself well into
this particular ecosystem, you know, it
does provides a structure and it
allows us to include metadata also.
But there's one thing I mentioned
this before. Finally, what actually is
fed into the digital assistance. Or
chat, GPD or whatever that is
flat printed so they make sense
of information that is in text
form. So how do we, you
know, cross that bridge that we
have content written in detail, very
well tagged and also annotated for
you?Single source for different
audiences, different locale, uh, sorry,
locales, yeah, uh, you know, for
global audience. And then we are
required to generate something in text.
So that is a do you
think there is still a need
for data in this scenario?Now,
can we find something else that could
supplant data, uh, when it comes to, you
know, the well structured content? Uh, is
there another format, another rival
format or anything else that could do the
job well?Asked
for AI and right now it's
the best that's you know, it
performs better than any anything else.
Um, markdown is the second best.
And the reason the second best is because
a lot of um.
A lot of the technology
for delivering content it has
like native markdown, but markdown
has its limitations. And so
how do you compensate for
those limitations? Well, you know,
so it really is, is
is is. The and the
reason that that it is the
best is because the markdown is,
uh, sorry, the markup is richer.
So what you're writing is really
important now. So if you say
it, I'll use the noun instead
of it, right? So if it's.
The the P2240, call it the
P2240 all the time. Don't say
it because. The AI,
the LM, is going to be reading
the text. Now you could say it
everywhere and then you would have to
put the metadata in for P2240 because
that distinguishes it from the P2241 and
the P2242 and the P42243. Or you
could just do it. In
the text itself, so
it's not as important
anymore to have um,
uh. For example,
an entire topic. Yeah, I mean, topics
are still good because when you need
to read the entire topic, it's there.
But if you just need that one
piece of information, then the one
sentence can do the trick.
But if the sentence is poorly
written, then it's not going to
be useful for the LM, right?
So it's it. This is where
it all comes together. And and
as I said, can the LM
use unstructured content? Yes, it can.
But it doesn't give you good results.
So the best results are still with
with dinner because dinner was built for
that kind of, um.
That kind of delivery before its time it
was built for that kind of delivery if
you used it or well, because there are
more than one way to use data and
sometimes people aren't putting the
tagging in and they aren't doing the
information architecture in a way that's
going to be useful. So this goes back to
what are the goals. That you're
trying like the business goals, then what
are the objectives? And then what is, you
know, what are your practices and what
tools are you using? And so you have to
start there to know whether you're doing
it right up at the beginning.
Right. So structured content and use of
data is a couple of takeaways that
I can understand from this. Uh, apart
from that, uh, looking across everything
well that we discussed the challenges,
foundations and day-to-day practices,
what are the key takeaways that you
would want the people who are attending?
Right, though, uh, to carry with them as
they prepare for a different content
delivery key take away. So I, I think
we kind of touched on them already. So
one is to start with, what is the
return on investment that you wanna get
that your business wants to get? Like is
their goal to reduce support?Is
their goal to have self-service? Is
their goal to have 100% accurate
delivery? And then, uh.
Work backwards from there to figure out
what you want to do and how you
need to do it.
No, that's the the first one
and the second one. Is that
because the second aspect is that
because the the field is progressing
so quickly, just keep learning. Yeah,
there are a number of people
talking about. How they
use AI and how they're experimenting
with it and, um, you know,
learn from them. I, I published
recently a series of people to
follow who talk about AI and
LinkedIn, and I think there were
12 or 13 of them. And
so those are some folks to start with,
um, and semantics folks, there's, um.
Uh, Jessica Talisman and a few others I,
I can't remember, uh, Larry Swanson. You
could always share the names later. You
can always share the names later. Yeah.
So, you know, just learn from them so it
doesn't happen. When I say learn, it
doesn't mean ohh, I have to sign up for
a course and take a course and spend
every. Uh, weeknight doing this sometimes
it's just in five minute increments here
and there. Yeah. You know, Michael Leon
Tosca is a great one to, to follow on
LinkedIn. So you just read one of his
posts and that's it for, you know, the
day or for the week. And now you've
learned a little something and it will
give you that that.
That lead is like being a detective and
finding these clues to, you know, what do
I want to do? How can I do this
better? How can I make it easier for
myself? How can I meet those business
goals? So you have to just keep keep
sleuthing. Probably make
use of something like Notebook LM AI to
figure out this information for you and
give you the gist of it. So that's
a great way to do that.
That is great for that.
So thank you so much for
all these insights and that gives
our listeners a solid view of
both the strategic and practical size
of preparing AI driven content delivery.
And now I'm going to open
the floor for Q&A and let's
hear questions. For our audiences, have
any so, uh, their audience, I
am unmuting you. You go ahead
and ask your questions and you
can also put those in chat.
I just want to say your session was so
good, that's why we didn't have
questions. Oh, oh,
thank you.
Ohh, they could add some
value, yeah. Hi everybody.
Just was wondering, uh, in all this talk
that is there a trade off between making
our content more readable for AI? Does it
become less, uh, less consumable by human
beings? Like I mean, the example that you
gave where you don't write it right? So
you, you kind of putting the name again.
So it seemed like. The natural way for
humans to read it, yeah, just for one
thing. What are your thoughts? Like, I
mean, does it have to be, uh, two ways?
Like, I mean, better for AI, better for
humans, or is it going to be better for
both?It's a, that's
an excellent question actually. And, and,
um, I'm glad you're giving me
the opportunity to cover it. So
let's think about it this way.
Is that the consumer is the
third line of, of consumption because
first it's, um. The the
LM or the AI that's consuming your
content and then it's through the search
engine or the delivery portal and then
it's from the person. So if it's
not a machine readable, it's never going
to make it to the person because
there will be somebody's stuff who's more
machine readable. Than yours if you're
looking at it from that like a search
engine perspective. If it's, if it's a
self-contained, that's a bit of a
different story. I would counter that the
UM.
The principles of like plain language
and and modularity and so on,
where everything is kind of
self-contained. I don't think that
dropping it and using like the
proper noun is actually making it
less readable for a person. I
think it's actually making it more
readable. For a person, because
they've shown that, uh.
People in today's world don't really
understand how modifiers work. So when
you say it, they don't know
what it's modifying. So it's and
particularly if you have someone for
whom English is the second or
third language, and this goes for,
you know. In any language, when
you stop to think about it,
um, when you stop to think
about language, um, you're, you're
really, um. Looking
at clearer for the end user, but
it's also making it clearer for the
intermediary steps, which is the AI and
then the search engine.
Or the chat bot.
And boy is adding to what trial as
saying we are already seeing this change
in behavior of human behavior. They don't
want to go to a help hotel or
search for it. They would rather pick up
their phone probably and ask a question
to say Gemini or perplexity or if they
have their companies. Own chat boards,
they would ask the question directly in
natural language. In that case, the way
the content was written, if it says
P22 instead of eight, it doesn't matter
to the human reader also because they
are consuming it the same way, you
know, through the machine. So that is
a marked behavior change and because of
it, I don't think the content in the
back, you know, under the hood and the
content that is being delivered, there's
a slight difference. What do you say
right about that?
What is delivered is more attuned to the
audience. Well, what is delivered
is, you know, generative. So it's
generated and it's depending on. So like,
you know, not all elements are good at
the same thing. And so, um, some LM's
will be better at kind of analysis and
others will be better at the kind of,
you know, ohh. Editorial aspects.
So when you're thinking about,
um, content, really just think
about the user, but also
follow the the principles like
plain language principles and natural
language processing principles and so
on to to think about.
How to make it clear? So going back
to like, you know how we have the
dosage right? So if you have I I
want to know the dosage for an infant,
it's going to be very clear. If you
say the dosage for an infant is instead
of saying you know. The
dosage is right because the dosage is
1 teaspoon maybe 3 paragraphs before you
said, you know, here the, the, the,
the, the, the categories. And now you
say the dosage is this the. And
so if you're reading the whole thing,
it'll be easy for you to understand
that. You mentioned the audiences in
this order and now you're talking about
it in this order, but the machine won't
understand that, and because of that, it
might get delivered to the user the wrong
way. So if you are very, very clear
and you're thinking about clarity for the
machine, then you're also thinking about
clarity for the user. That almost
as a proxy. You're using a machine as a
proxy for the user. I don't know if that
makes sense. Right, I think,
I think it all depends on um, you
know, how correct is the answer given by
the machine. So I'm sure that if the
answer is precise, people will definitely
prefer to do that.
Instead of, you know, actually going
through the docs. So yeah, makes sense.
But yeah, I, I mean, like maybe it
was a bad example. Uh, some examples
could be like maybe you could put more
images for humans, but maybe I would not
understand that very well. Or perhaps
tables, you know, maybe I gets. Confused
with tables that gets thrown off. I don't
know that that's true.
So, you know, and now this comes back
to what I said earlier about rethinking
the way we do content, because if you
think about like, what is the, what is
the purpose of all text? Well, the
purpose of all text is to describe what's
going on in an image. So yeah, if
you think about different learners.
Different learning styles. Yeah, image is
great, but you could also include the
alt text that makes it readable or
you know, you're describing the image
that makes it readable for the machine
so it can deliver things to the
the consumer and I don't know enough
about.
Like reading the captions of images and
all the different LM's and so on
and so forth. So I don't want
to mislead you, but it's worth
experimenting with those things so that
you know which LM is better for
your particular use case. Because let's
say you're doing API. Documentation for
developers, well, that's a very
different use case than, um,
delivering, um, um.
Medical information to the average
person, right? So you, you, you
want to say, OK, well, when
I'm doing this API documentation, uh,
what are the questions that the
developers are going to ask so
that I can have that information,
um. You know, kind of go through the
LM and go through the the search engine
to them or however it's being delivered
to them. And that's kind of what, you
know, when you're thinking about content
curation and then context curation,
that's what we're talking about is making
sure that it's going to work for the
person at the other end. And it's
got to work for all the intermediaries
before it can get to that person. But
it should be good for both. It shouldn't
favor the machines over the users, but it
should be equally good for both purposes.
That's a very good insight, so.
We are about to wrap up this
conversation now and thank you everyone
for your thoughtful questions. And a
special thank you to Ryan for sharing
such value with insights with us today.
It has been rich and in Azure
using conversation. So folks, it's time
to wrap up. I hope to
welcome you back in the coming year
for more conversations as the space
continues to evolve. And one more thing,
do watch out for follow up post
to this conversation. And I'm going to
bother right to share all the names
that she had forgotten. Right now, but
I'm sure she will share all the names of
the people she wants us to watch out for
and follow. And also I need tools that
she herself make use of to say add
metadata or create knowledge graphs and
whatnot. So her tool recommendations and
people recommendations are going to be in
that follow up.
So I guess until then,
bye bye to you all
and happy 2026.
Bye, bye. Thanks for for having me.
Bye. Thank you. Thank you everyone.